scissors glue burns card the details
剪刀 胶水
about these are all explained in v-folds
这些在教程1里已经解释过了
tutorial part 1 so there are five kinds
这是五种V形折
of default the first is the the right
第一种是直角V形折
angle v-folds this is explained in part
在上节教程详细讲解了
1 the second is the cute angle default
锐角V形折也一样
this is also explained in part 1 the
第三种山形V折
third is the pointed v-fold this we're
和第四种钝角V形折
going to deal with in this tutorial the
是本节课就要讲解的
tutorial and finally it's the asymmetric
最后一种非对称V形折
v-fold this will be in v-folds tutorial
是V形折第三部分内容
part 3 okay we're going to start by
进入正题吧
making a pointed v-fold so start with
首先制作个山形V折
the base sheet fold the card in half no
取出底页卡纸 对折
need to measure no need to score with
没必要测量的太细
this weight of cards at 160 g SN crease
我用的是160克的卡纸
it really thoroughly fold it back on
对折要很彻底
itself crease it again you can't crease it too much
如果觉得已经很到位了
it too much so fold it back up itself a
翻过来再折一次
couple more times and really crease it
一定要确保折彻底
well this is this is the base sheet
这就是基本页了
having it well creased means that the
折痕越彻底立体结构
pop-up will move more sweetly so we
活动起来就越顺滑
might as well make a say a red one take
来张红色的卡纸吧
your sheet of cards again no need to
取出卡纸同样不用严格测量
measure just cut it in half
剪一半
fold it in half no need to measure just
对折 同样没必要测太细
do it by eye again as with all creases
目测即可
crease it really really thoroughly fold
两边都要
it back on itself
折到彻底
this time you make the fold from corner
这次是角对角对折
to corner so you're doing a diagonal
沿对角线的
fold corner to corner with it with it
对折即可
folded in half so there's no wrong way
理论上不会出啥错
to do this because it's symmetrical it
两面都是对称的
it can go either way fold it back on itself again
可以任意方向再折叠一次
again so when you open it up you have an arrow
展开 得到个箭头
arrow all three all three creases are
三个折痕都
meeting at the same point and those
汇聚到同一个点
those extra creases the diagonal ones again
那些额外折痕又汇聚到对角线
you can reinforce those one more time
你可以再次加强它们
now this is going to sit on your on your page like this
它将像这样固定在页面
page like this so one question is how tight you want it
要看你的立体结构
tight you want it what actual shape of
实际想呈现成什么样
pop-up you want do you want a really
是想要挺点的V形折
tight V fold or do you want a really
还是比较平坦的
flat shape you can even go all the way
甚至是完全放平的
flat and it will still work so I'll go
都不是问题
for something like this the second
我先做成这样
question is what you do with the with
第二个要考虑点是
with the flaps you can either cut them down
想对侧襟做什么文章
into narrow flaps of v underneath
你可以把它们剪小点藏在V折底下
it or you can leave them out wide and
也可以保留着露外面
you can use these these folds for making
利用折角制作些反折景层
that counter folds in so I'm going to do
我下面演示下
that turn it into counter folds so we
制作反折
start just cut into the cat into the
折边叠起来
folded edge so say we just do a couple
沿这边剪出两个折
like this here fold it over just crease
折出折痕
it well this one I've made the two cuts
我剪得两个折长度不一样
at different lengths so that will give
这就产生出
us a slightly different shape in the
两个略有不同的形状
pop-up open it up and push those through
打开并把它们推进去
so that's one this is the other
一个 再来一个
so that's the that's the shape we're
这就成了。
going to get on it on the top crease you
你当然可以给侧
can now do the same on the bottom crease
折痕做同样事情 两侧都行
the bottom two creases so if we want it
如果想让两侧对称
all symmetric we do it all with the two
可以同时操作两边侧襟
folds to two outer flaps fold it up make
把两边折起来
some cuts into those just do a couple
剪出两个反折
here there's a lot of room for creativity in this
这里有很大的创作空间
creativity in this and understanding
一些没固化要求的操作
understanding something really a really simple option but you know
你如果练习下就会很容易懂
but you know if you make your own you
在制作时
can really play around with these you
你可以随意尝试
can make them longer narrower multiple
像反折的长短、宽窄、数量这些
there's all sorts of options so we'll
都行的 继续看这个
open this one up push these through one
打开并把反折推起来 一个
two three four push these ones down so
两个 三个 四个  顶上是推进去
this is a shape you're gonna have now
这就是效果啦
again you can decide that you want these
然后你要决定
other flaps left as part of the design
剩下的侧襟怎么处理 是当做设计的一部分
or you might decide to trim them down so
还是修剪掉
I'm going to trim them down so again
这里我是剪掉了
I'll just follow this sort of very
呼应下这个尖尖的形状
pointy pointy shape so I'm just going to
从侧面开始
cut it like this to the to the point so
剪到定点为止
this is what your pop-up is going to be
这就是立体结构要呈现的样子
like now again you can decide you want
现在你可以决定
it really tight or do you want quite a
是要更紧点还是宽点
quite a wide shape so I'm gonna go for
这里我保持这个样子了
something like this
start by gluing one side with all these
开始上胶水
all pop ups you need you need symmetry
这时立体结构要对称
so we're just glue one side smear the
我们从一侧开始上胶水
glue right up to the crease I tend to
我喜欢用小拇指
use my little finger so then all my
这样我其他指头可以不受影响
other fingers stay free from glue and I
can I can use them to touch other things
去碰别的东西
without cars sticking to them so there
也不怕误粘住
so there we go
好了
stick one side down maybe move it in a
一侧向下 微调下
little bit more make sure the central crease
确保中间折痕
crease is lined up with the Central
跟基础页中折线是在一排
Valley of the base
fold the whole thing into its closed
所有折页放回到收起位置
给另一粘口上胶水
涂匀
合上基础页
就酱
也许反折就这样放着了
设计就是这样
另一种用法 这些反折可以当肌肉用
支撑其他的元素
我来演示下
拿出点卡纸剪成片
来做实验
你也可以剪成
任何想要的形状或大小
像我这 剪得就很放飞了
把胶水涂到相对小的面上
不要涂到大的面
会导致粘到你并不想被粘的地方
这会是把胶水涂给相对小的反折
粘上刚剪出的那片
确认下粘牢了
对称位置不妨也弄个
刚粘这片纸尺寸
有点头重脚轻
等会再来修剪下
把这个粘上
也可以给反折的
另一个面粘些元素
这就来做一对吧
尝试下所有的
可能性
给两侧上胶水 给这边竖一个
另一边也这样竖一个
也可以在顶上
这四个面(两个反折)
做文章
我来演示下
剪出个略窄能放得下的纸条
对折下
这里不一定是对折
如果设计是非对称的
在纸条合适位置
折叠即可
上胶水
让纸条能在这卡住
添加好后 合上基本页
牢牢按一会
这就成型了
这是个抽象形状
可以从各方向观看
没那种是 对的错的
你可以正着
背着
甚至俯视 俯视翻转
没错 看抽象的作品
你开心就好
这个凹槽两面也能扩展
剪两片小点的卡纸片
给凹槽里上胶水
得到个露出来的纸条
另一个也一样
貌似有点不太均衡
我把另一个修齐
这就是山形V折啦
下面看个例子
这里是个山形V折
尾部被剪掉了
两头都被做成反折
用来撑起手脚
画面上另一个元素
是个小的V折制作的头
这是一对山形V折
来看些书的例子
《十只小怪兽》
这页是个山形V折
这里是侧襟
侧襟被融入到设计里
这里把元素
粘在了两个侧面
而不是反折上
头也是同理
从底部前方观察
能很直观的看明白
来看《丛林岁月》
这里树干运用了山形V折
一边还叠加了
另一个V形折
撑起人物
还用了插槽实现树枝伸出效果
总之 这里关注的关键点
树干是山形V折
最后看下《穿靴子的猫》
六十年代的作品
画面中有两个山形V折
这边是个较明显的山形V折
这边是个
被大幅裁掉的山形V折
所有折痕都汇聚向
主轴上同一点
顺着这个折痕
这个
和这个折痕
就能验证这种关系 以上就是山形V折
fold now we'll move on to the obtuse
我们继续钝角V折
angle default this one but this is the
这个就是钝角V折
obtuse angle V fold the angles on each
每个边上
side of the central crease of the pop up
基础面和中心折线
are more than 90 degrees it's quite an
呈的角度超过90度
unusual mechanism you don't see it very
这种结构比较稀罕 不太常见
often I'll show you how to make one of
我来演示下如何制作
these so take a base crease it well this
拿出张卡纸做基础页
time we take out take the other half
认真对折下
sheet of cards fold this in the middle
拿出另一半卡纸做立体结构
crease it crease it thoroughly and then
从中间对折  折彻底
this time here's the is the folded edge
这次是沿折角
start about a third of the way up and
大概三分之一位置
fold it downwards to the outer edges of
向外边角折下来
the card so here it is fold it well when
确定折彻底了
you when you open this up you see that
展开后
you've got an upward pointing arrow
能看到类似向上箭头的折痕
mostly with with them acute angle
在锐角V折里
v-folds you'll have a downward pointing
通常会是向下箭头
arrow that's the normal that's what
you're usually looking for but in this
在这里箭头是向上
case the creases form an arrow pointing
up now cut out the from the point where
从边上折痕开始地方开始
all the creases meet you just cut out a
剪出比较窄的锲子形状
thin wedge you cut gluing tabs on to the
然后剪出粘口
bottom cut off the end oh I'll make that
在最后面
a bit bit tighter so this is your this
剪紧一点收尾
is your obtuse angle we let this
这就是锐角V折了
re-crease these these sand falls a bit
再加强下折痕
and doing a bit more thoroughly if your
如果折的不到位
folds up thoroughly enough crease leave
打开时就不是那么顺畅
the pop-up either won't open
所以
clothes very well so it's very important
折彻底真非常重要
to increase it well this is going to sit
放基本页上会是这样
on your page like this you can go quite
你可以拉宽一点
wide you can go quite tight but if you
也可以挺一点
go too wide you'll see it starts lifting off
但如果拉过宽 会把页面绷起来
off the page so according to the angles
所以角度决定
you've made and that will dictate how
能展开宽度的阈值
wide you can go so again we stick down
先来粘一侧
one side this symmetries is always
important by cutting the by making the
fold with it folded in half we get
symmetrical angles on the pop-up and now
the way we stick it down we're going to
get symmetrical angles on the pant so
there it is stick down one side make
sure the the central crease in the
pop-up is lined up with the gully gully
of the base fold the whole thing shut to
press it well put glue on the other the
给另一个粘口上胶水
other tab
smear the glue right up to the crease
把胶水在折痕要涂匀
that's pretty important
这相当重要
fold it sucks there we go the two single
盖起来压牢 钝角折就成了
V fold this is this is quite interesting
这蛮有意思的
because the the central crease of the
中间折线有向后倒的感觉
pop-up falls backwards the other one
另一种会有向后倾倒感
that the central gully will lean
的立体结构是
backwards is the right angle V fold
直角V形折
so here's a version these are the right
angle v-folds the angles on the bottom a
90 degrees whereas on this one they're
more than 90 and these ones because it
because it falls down backwards and I
think the higher you want the pop up
that the nearer the front it has to be
yeah I'll just show you in a couple of
examples of obtuse angle V faults this
is one you can see it just leans back
slightly so that that works nicely for
this design I've got one book that has
them as a to tangle V fold and a pointed
V fold in it so here it is the the book
is Bow Wow by Chuck Murphy and this this
is it under the triangle you open it up
there's the pyramid is a pointed V fold
and the dog is an obtuse angle V Falls
and the best way to see this is to look
at the back of the design and there you
can see the the central crease of the
dog is leaning backwards so the dog is
obtuse angle V fold the pyramid is a
pointed v-fold and that fits at some
v-folds part to all the information I'm
giving you is in booths my book pop-up
design from paper mechanics